Gold in Blood!
血中金
You remember.
你还记得
One of the mysterious Heluo alchemic skills.
河络炼金秘籍之一
An alchemist’s body is like strong armor.
练成者在周身如披铁甲
Your throat is as hard as iron.
阁下咽喉硬如精铁
You must be a great alchemist.
想必是个中高手
Step aside!
让路
No way!
休想
Master,
师父
this assassin’s moves are bizarre.
这刺客的招式好怪异啊
Haishi, stay on your toes.
海市 你要当心
Your Majesty, take the sword.
陛下 接刀
Let’s end this in your tribal way.
按草原的规矩
Wrestle!
来摔跤吧
Your Majesty, go!
陛下快走
No!
不
It’s said Alchemy
都说这如今天下
and Wind Waking
炼金 召风
have been lost.
都已绝迹世间
It’s quite unexpected
想不到传人
they’re carried on in foreign tribes.
竟然都在外族
Don’t you find that interesting?
你不觉得颇有意思吗
Protect His Majesty.
保护陛下
Kill me.
杀我
Grant me the glory of a warrior.
予我战士之荣耀
See you in the Nether.
泉下再会
Your Majesty.
陛下
You both have done well protecting me.
你们两个护驾有功
Tell me.
说吧
What reward do you want?
想要什么赏赐
I’m afraid it’s too much to ask.
臣恐太僭越
Whatever it is that the country can offer,
只要国中有
you’ll have it.
皆可自取
If Your Majesty says so.
那臣就不客气了
Don’t!
不要
Jianming!
鉴明
Master!
师父
Lord!
公爷
Jianming.
鉴明
I’m Duohan.
我是夺罕
Get him back.
抓他回来
Yes.
是
Your Majesty,
陛下
I’ve been keeping a rebel.
臣豢养了谋逆之徒
Zhuoying...
卓英
He must have a painful reason to do so.
卓英应该是有难言之隐
Jianming,
鉴明
once again,
你又一次
you took a blow for me.
挡在了朕的身前
You always say that Jincheng Palace
你总说这金城宫
has no shadows
是无影之宫
where secrets can lurk.
什么都藏匿不住
But in the end,
可谁想到头来
it’s the man in eternal light
正是这些长明之灯
that nearly took your life.
几乎就要了你的命
What’s the point of being so persistent?
何必执着呢
For those promises?
就为了那些约定
Let go.
放手吧
You don’t owe me anything anymore.
你早已不亏欠朕什么了
Master.
师父
Bring Zhuoying back.
把卓英带回来
If you can’t do that,
如若不行
kill him.
便杀了他
Master...
师父
Kill Fang Zhuoying.
杀了方卓英
He’s in a frenzy.
他狂态大发
I’m afraid no one else
只怕旁人
is a match for him,
都不是他的对手
except you.
但你可以
He’s your brother,
他是你哥
and won’t hurt you.
会对你手下留情的
Lord,
公爷
I’ve dressed the wound.
这回伤口处理完了
You must be careful in the future.
日后可千万要当心哪
I’ll make some medicine for you.
属下为您去熬药
Be back soon.
随后便回
Young Master Haishi.
小公子
Master.
师父
How many people have you killed?
您究竟杀过多少人
Countless.
不计其数
When was the last time
您上次杀人
you killed someone?
是在什么时候
In the fake princess’s suppression.
伪帝姬之乱
Liar!
你骗人
It was yesterday.
就在昨日
You killed Zheliu.
你杀了柘榴
According to the secret guards,
暗卫说
you dismissed the staffs of Fabric Office
你调开了绫锦司的人
and talked to Zheliu for a while.
你跟柘榴谈了片刻
You killed her with just a few words.
便用几句话杀了她
And Aunt Su.
还有苏姨
You killed her too, didn’t you?
也被你灭口了吧
Do you think she’d curse you
你猜她临死之前
a painful death before she died?
会不会咒你不得好死
What exactly do you want Zhuoying
你究竟要卓英
to do for you?
为你做些什么
Zhuoying is a man
卓英这个人
who puts his promises before his life.
重承诺胜过性命
Since you took him under your wing,
自从被你收服
he’s been loyal to you ever since.
一直跟随至今
He has never
你的命令
disobeyed any of your orders.
他可曾有过丝毫的违背
Even if Zheliu killed herself soon after
即便柘榴从昶王府回来
she came back from Lord Chang’s Mansion,
便自尽了
Zhuoying would seek revenge
卓英要报复
on Lord Chang,
也只会去找昶王
instead of His Majesty.
也找不到陛下那儿
Master,
师父
is it really you?
真的是你吗
Why did Zheliu have to die?
为什么柘榴必须要死呢
She’s just a
她只是一个
blind orphan.
孤苦无依的盲女
Zhuoying loves her
卓英爱惜她
as much as he loves his own life.
如同爱惜自己的性命
When he found her dead,
柘榴死了
he wailed.
卓英哭得好大声
I doubt if he would
他怕是这辈子
cry again for the rest of his life.
再也哭不出来了
That’s why the blind girl had to die.
所以这个盲女不得不死
If she didn’t die,
若她不死
she’d be a weakness for Zhuoying.
卓英永远有弱点
Master.
师父
You’ll never have any weaknesses,
您永远不会有任何弱点
right?
对吧
What are you trying to say?
你想说什么
Zhuoying and I
卓英与我
are like brothers
像兄弟
and best friends.
像朋友
We drink and practice together,
我们可以豪饮论剑
and ride side by side,
并驾齐驱
like real brothers.
亲如一胞同出
But you’re my master,
而您是我的师父
my...
您是
Master, you’re so cruel.
师父 您的心好冷啊
All of us, including Zheliu,
即便是柘榴
Zhuoying,
即便是卓英
and those who pledged
即便是那些发誓
their loyalty to you
永远向您效忠的人
are merely your pawns
也如同您手中的棋子
who are expendable, aren’t we?
随时可弃吧
Young Master Haishi.
小公子
A word from the palace.
宫里传话来
The troops have been assembled.
大徵军已集结完毕
They’re urging an immediate departure.
催促即刻动身哪
Tell them
回他们
the young master is on the way.
小公子立刻去
Yes.
是
Master,
师父
did you raise us
您养育我们长大
to see us
就是为了看我们
kill each other?
自相残杀吗
Can I trust you anymore?
我究竟还能信您多少呢
Mr. Fang,
方大人
the traitor Duohan
逆贼夺罕
is hiding in this hut.
就藏在这处草屋里面
I know you’re under an imperial order.
我知道你有皇命在身
Come on.
来吧
Mr. Fang,
方大人
will your wound be alright?
您的伤无大碍吧
Fang Jianming
这个方鉴明
really impressed me
倒是有能耐
by killing two of
折损我鹄库
my best men.
两大得力干将
Lord, what’s our next move?
王 可有下一步行动
Since
既然
a few assassins can’t kill
杀掉帝旭与方鉴明
Emperor Xu and Fang Jianming,
并非个人能力所为
I have to assemble an army
那我只好发动大军
and go all out.
全力而为了
Are you saying
王是想
that we attack Huangquan Pass?
攻打黄泉关
Have you established contact
苏鸣留下的暗线
with Su Ming’s undercover?
你可联系上了
Yes, I have.
联系上了
He’s willing to help us
他愿意帮助我们
avenge Su Ming’s death.
为苏鸣报仇
But Huangquan Pass is a hard nut to crack.
可是黄泉关易守难攻
I know what you mean.
我知道你意思
I don’t want to lose too many men, either.
我也不想折损太多人马
You mean?
那王是
Lord Chang
昶王
intends to join forces with me to attack Tianqi.
欲与我联手攻打天启
But now it’s autumn.
但如今已是秋日
Soon winter will be upon us,
不久寒冬将至
not the best time
并不是发起攻击的
to launch an attack.
最好时机
We’ve discussed.
我与他商讨
In the next spring,
待到来年春暖花开之时
he’ll stage an uprising in the city,
他在城中起事
and I will attack Huangquan Pass.
我在外面攻打黄泉关
We’ll join forces
我们里应外合
and take Dazheng down.
拿下大徵
Mr. Fang,
没想到
I’m sorry you have to come back
方大人这次回到黄泉关
to Huangquan Pass on such a mission.
竟是这番情景
Mr. Fang,
方大人
it’s late in the afternoon.
已是午后时分
But none of the ten scouts have returned.
但那十名探马无一归来
What’s worse,
而且
since we heard two warning horns
草原上曾先后响起
from the grassland,
两声警示鸣笛
there has been no further news.
之后便再无消息
I’m afraid the scouts have been killed.
这十人恐怕已遭不测
In case Fang Zhuoying’s friends set him free,
清海公为防故旧徇私
Lord Qinghai selected 500 men
出城后的五百人马
from Beifu Army instead of Secret Force
不在暗卫中选拔
to hunt him down.
而选自于北府军
I heard
听说
most of them were once Mr. Fu’s men
多数都是符大人
from Huangquan Pass.
在黄泉营带过的部下
- Mhm. - But Mr. Fang, you and the men
可方大人带着他们
have tried several times
追击半月
in half a month to round him up.
数次围剿
Fang Zhuoying is all alone.
那方卓英只孤身一人
He’s like a ghost.
行踪如同鬼魅
It’s thousands of kilometers
从中州至瀚州
from Zhongzhou to Hanzhou.
数千里路途
Yet we failed to capture him.
拿他不着
Instead, we lost a few
反赔进去几名
excellent fighters.
精壮的汉子
Now Fang Zhuoying
如今方卓英
has gone over Mount Piluo,
自毗罗山翻越而过
and ten more lives are lost.
又是十条人命的损失
It seems
看来
he’s really hard to seize.
他真是难以缉拿
Now that he’s
他如今
entered Jiamanese territory,
已经进入迦满境内
it’s not proper for the remaining 400 men,
剩余的四百骑
being neither envoys
既非使节
or merchants,
亦非商贾
to cross the border
不便公然武装
fully armed.
进入他族之地
Mr. Fu and I will go after him
我便同符大人一起
with a few men.
轻装简行便可
Mr. Fang,
方大人
I’ll take care of
缉拿方卓英之事
Fang Zhuoying’s arrest.
就交给我吧
No.
不可
Master gave the task to me.
这件事是师父交给我的
I must be the one to do it.
必须由我来做
You should stay at Huangquan Pass.
你便留在黄泉营内吧
When are you going to ride out?
何时出发
Right now.
即刻出发
Is that him?
那是他吗
It looks like him.
看那样子
I think it’s him.
应该是
Look, Commanders!
大人快看
A Huku troop.
是鹄库人
Sir,
大人
when the traitor
要是逆贼
blends in the Huku troop,
躲入鹄库军阵中
there’ll be no way we can hunt him down.
就无可挽回了
Who would have known
谁曾想
that the traitor summoned a Huku troop
这逆贼竟勾结鹄库军
to meet him here?
在此接应
So now,
此刻
I guess only Mr. Fang can shoot him down
恐怕只有方大人的羽箭
with his arrows.
才能追上了
Let me give it a try.
让我一试
Zhuoying,
卓英
this is the last bet
这是师父和你
between you and me.
最后一场赌
If you believe in your brotherhood
若你相信海市
with Haishi
平日待你的情分
and that he would rather disobey my order
相信他宁可抗命
than kill you,
也不会杀你的话
take this bet.
咱们就赌上这一场
If you win,
如果你赢了
the reward will be your freedom
就赢得自由
and the vast land of Hanzhou.
和这七千里的瀚州
I won’t hide.
我不会躲闪
You have to shoot your target.
你这一箭 非中不可
I believe
我相信你
you can hit me.
一定能中
Mr. Fang,
方大人
are you sure you won’t rest for a few days?
当真不在营中休养几日
Mr. Fu can set out
复命之事
for Tianqi City first
有符大人
and report to His Majesty.
返回天启城即可
Yes.
是啊
Mr. Fang,
方大人
your wound hasn’t healed.
你的伤势还没好
It’s too soon for you to ride out.
这就赶路
Why don’t you take some time to rest
要不休养些时日
before riding back?
再启程也不迟啊
Winter comes early in Hanbei.
瀚北冬季来得早
If it snows, the roads will be blocked.
一旦下雪 必然阻途
I’d better get back to Tianqi as soon as possible
我还是尽早赶回天启
and report to my master and His Majesty.
向师父还有陛下复命
If you insist,
方大人执意如此
I will say no more.
汤某也不便强留
Mr. Fu.
符大人
Yes.
在
Please take care of Mr. Fang
方大人这一路
on your way back.
还得有劳你多照顾
Sure.
是
Let’s say goodbye here.
便送到这儿吧
So long.
后会有期
General Fang,
方将军
it’s Chishan City up ahead.
前边就是赤山城了
Mr. Fang!
方大人
General!
将军
Now,
快
take Mr. Fang to Chishan City.
把方大人送进赤山城
Yes.
是
Mr. Fang was wounded,
方大人受了伤
and rode day and night.
又日夜兼程地赶路
He coughed blood.
后来又吐了血
Now he’s unconscious due to fever.
如今高烧不醒
Please check
你且看看
his condition.
他到底如何了
Sir,
大人
can we have a word alone?
借一步说话
how is Mr. Fang’s
方大人的病情
condition?
到底如何了
You can tell me.
你但说无妨
Sir,
回大人
the commander has an old wound.
这位大人本有旧伤
Due to the long ride
又连日奔波
and cold weather,
加上天气转凉
she caught a cold.
受了风寒
Yes, she’s a woman.
她又是个女子
It’s too much a blow
难免气血两虚
for her body to manage.
一时撑不过来啊
Are you sure?
你可确认无误
I’ve been a physician for 30 years.
小的行医三十载
I can tell men from women
这男女之症嘛
by checking
只要一号脉
their pulses.
便能诊得出来
The weather is far too cold.
天气如此寒凉
If there are women on your journey,
若真想携带女眷
I suggest they ride a carriage
该当乘坐车辇
with
在车辇内
burning charcoal in it.
放些炭火好些啊
You’re right, sir.
郎中 你所言极是
Mm-hmm.
不过本官如此安置
to make such an arrangement.
便有如此安置的道理
Right.
那是
This news concerns your life.
此事攸关身家性命
Do you understand?
你可知否
Yes, I do.
小人知道
You...
你
Who are you?
你是何人
Mr. Fang.
方大人
Mr. Fu.
符大人
Is the fever gone?
方大人的热可是退了
You still
看样子
don’t look well.
气色仍是不大好啊
Maybe the prescription isn’t working.
莫非是方子开得不对症
No. It is working,
方子是对的
except that it’s not working well.
但并不高明
The fever goes down a bit,
热 渐渐低了
but is not completely gone.
但难退
Mr. Fang,
方大人
we’ve been staying in Chishan City
我们在赤山城
for quite some days.
已逗留多日了
But I haven’t seen
但符某未曾见
any improvement in your health.
方大人有所好转
And the capital is waiting for our report.
那边又急于回去复命
Shall I
不若
lead the men out first?
我带大部队先行出发
When you’re cured,
待方大人彻底痊愈之后
you can catch up with us.
再赶上大队
What do you think?
如何
That’s a great plan, Mr. Fu.
全听符大人安排
When you were unconscious,
在您受伤期间
Xiaoliu had been looking after you.
驿馆的小六忙前忙后的
I can tell
我倒看那姑娘
she’s a caring girl,
是个仔细人
so I paid her
所以给了她些碎金
to look after you.
托她代为照顾方大人
Thank you.
有劳了
Then I’ll gather the men and set off.
那符某便召集人马
Mr. Fang,
方大人
take care of yourself.
好生诊治
I’ll see you when you catch up.
符某等方大人赶上来
Please, Mr. Fu.
符大人请
Lord.
公爷
Come in.
进来
Fu Yi and the men
符义已经率领人马
have left Chishan for Tianqi City.
从赤山城前来天启城了
But Haishi’s wound hasn’t healed,
只是小公子伤势未愈
so he’s staying in an inn in Chishan City.
还在赤山城的驿馆休养
He’s been hunting Zhuoying
他追击卓英
for more than a month.
已有月余
Without proper treatment, his wound
伤势长此拖下去
could cause unimaginable damage.
后果堪舆
I asked you to prepare some medicine
之前让你们去备药
to be delivered to Chishan City.
快马送到赤山城
Have you prepared it?
都备好了吗
Yes, I have.
已经备好
However...
只是
What?
只是什么
I’m not sure if Haishi
只是公爷送去的药
will accept your medicine.
小公子怕是未必收啊
Tell him it’s from you.
就说是你送的吧
Yes, Lord.
是 公爷
Fang Jianming is sly.
方鉴明就是方鉴明啊
How sophisticated
好心机
and decisive!
好决断哪
To drag
为了将这祸水
Your Highness down,
引到殿下您身上
he even killed Zheliu.
竟连这柘榴都杀啦
Cunning fox.
那个老狐狸
What a brilliant plan
这手算盘打得是
it is!
好生精细呀
I’m sorry
要怪
that I’m not smart enough.
就怪奴婢不够伶俐
- I shouldn’t have... - Hey.
本不应该
Even if the blind girl didn’t die,
那盲女不死
Fang Zhuoying would keep
方卓英到关外
going against me in Hanzhou.
还是要与本王作对
The blind girl’s death
加上那盲女的一条命
only hardened
只不过使他
his heart.
心意更坚罢了
Like Commandery Princess Fenyang,
就好像汾阳郡主一样
even if she didn’t die,
即便她不死
I wouldn’t allow Emperor Xu
我也不能让帝旭
to have an easy life.
逍遥地活着了
I shouldn’t
这话
have told you this.
本不该对你说
Don’t worry, Your Highness.
殿下放心
My ears
奴婢这耳朵啊
are deaf
不该听的
to what I shouldn’t know.
什么都听不见
Smart man.
你倒是机灵
Since you’ve been in touch
既然你与左菩敦王
with Lord of Left Pudun,
暗通款曲
you must know my deal with him.
当知我们有约定
I dare not lie to Your Highness.
不敢瞒殿下
I do know.
奴婢知道
In the next spring,
明年开春之时
you will stage an uprising in Tianqi,
您在天启城起事
and the Left Lord will attack Huangquan Pass.
左王在黄泉关攻城
Together, your victory is secure.
里应外合 稳操胜券哪
Sadly,
可惜啊
Fang Jianming’s henchmen
方鉴明那些爪牙
are quite some eyesores.
十分碍眼
I’m not sure
就怕到时候
if they’ll get in my way.
行动不是很方便
Since they’re eyesores,
既是阻碍
why don’t Your Highness and I
那殿下为何不与我
get rid of these henchmen
在明年开春之前
before
将这些爪牙
the next spring comes?
悉数斩断呢
Sounds ambitious.
好大的口气
Who do you work for?
你身后到底是谁
Why let it bother you, Your Highness?
殿下何必纠结于此事呢
A shared goal makes us allies.
我们目标一致便是朋友
Your ally
既是朋友
will show himself
那总会有
when the day comes.
出现的那一日啊
The most reliable are the ones who are in it for profit.
熙攘利往 最为可靠
Go.
去
Gather flaws
去找方鉴明那些手下
of Fang Jianming’s men.
错漏之处
Stay low.
要不动声色
Make sure they’re eliminated.
要一击即中
Yes.
是
Commandery Princess Fenyang,
汾阳郡主
you were brave,
你空有胆色
but you knew no tactics.
智谋全无
You were a fool.
你太傻了
But for the sake
不过看在
that you didn’t
你到死都没
betray me in the end,
供出我的份上
I’ll make your death worth it.
我得让你死得值得
How far have you gotten?
看到哪里了
The page that she pulled out her pin
看到雪夜拨簪敲竹
to beat a bamboo on a snowy night.
那一页
It’s been years
朕也有好几年
since the last time I went out
没有在下雪的时候
on a snowy day.
出过门了
I don’t even remember
最近一次赏雪
the last time
是什么时候
I admired the snow view.
朕都不记得了
Would you like to see the snow?
陛下是想要赏雪吗
What’s so difficult about that?
这有什么难的
If Your Majesty
只要陛下
lends Eunuch Mu to me,
把穆内官借我一用
I can
今夜缇兰
make your wish come true tonight.
就可以让陛下一偿心愿
Blend these two.
把它们两个放在一起
Then scatter them
然后就带人到那上面
from up there.
放下来就行了
- Alright, I see. - Mm-hmm.
好好 奴婢知道了
You can count on me, Your Highness.
请淑容妃放心
Your Majesty.
陛下
Come with me, please.
跟臣妾来
There it is!
请陛下赏雪
Hold the ladder.
扶好点
- And hold it firm. - Yes, sure.
扶好点 是是是
Go.
来
How did you do it?
你是怎么做到的
Ice from the bottom of Yingge Sea,
缬罗花花粉和莺歌海
when blended with Xieluo pollen,
海底的冰晶相遇
turns into flakes.
就会化成雪晶
I gathered a lot of Xieluo pollen
臣妾夏天搜集了不少
in the summer.
缬罗花的花粉
Thought I could make some cakes for you.
本来想给陛下做点心
Unexpectedly,
没想到
it’s coming in handy now.
此时却派上用场了
How did you know
你是怎么知道
this method to make snow?
这样的方法的
It doesn’t snow in Zhunian all year round.
注辇终年无雪
When I was a kid,
小时候
I once blubbered for snow.
有一次我吵得太厉害了
So my mother
母妃就是用了
gave me
这样的方法
the first snow in my life
那是我人生中
in the same way.
第一次看到雪
Right.
对
On the west side of Jingcheng Hall,
敬诚堂的西侧
there’s also a bamboo grove.
也有一处竹林
When it snows this year,
等到今年下雪了
we’ll go there and pull out our pins
我们也去竹林里边
to beat the bamboos.
拨簪敲竹
By then,
到时候
you can hear the swish
你可以听到那些落雪
of snow falling
从竹叶上掉下来
from bamboo leaves.
唰唰的声音
The view is amazing.
雪景甚是美丽
We can also
我们还可以
drink a big bowl of warm tea.
喝一大碗热茶
And roast deer meat.
还可以烤鹿脯
And build snowmen.
还可以堆雪人
A lot of them.
堆好多好多雪人
We’ll paint eyes, noses
我们拿沾满松墨的笔
and mouths on them
给它们画眼睛
with a brush
画鼻子
and pine ink.
画嘴巴
What else can we do?
还可以干什么
We’ll see.
届时便知了
(Zichen Hall) Prince Duohan of Huku
鹄库王子夺罕
lurked in Jifeng Pavilion for decades.
潜居霁风馆多年
(Zichen Hall) The assassination is unpardonable.
行刺陛下 罪不可恕
Yet due to Fang Haishi’s negligence,
方海市又追击不利
he fled to Huku.
让他逃回鹄库
Although Lord Qinghai
虽则清海公
saved Your Majesty,
此番保护陛下有功
he should be held accountable for his apprentices.
但实在难逃失察之过
Your Majesty.
陛下
Lord Qinghai holds a prominent position
清海公身居要职
that concerns Your Majesty’s safety.
手握陛下安危命脉
His negligence
失察之过
rings an alarm.
令臣下等警醒
Punishment
不处罚
is essential to ease public anger.
不足以平息众怒
- We sincerely request for Lord Qinghai’s
请陛下以大徵天下为重
- punishment for the stability of Dazheng.
处罚清海公
- Please punish Lord Qinghai.
请陛下处罚清海公
Your Majesty,
陛下
I implore Your Majesty to think twice.
臣弟恳请陛下三思而行
Although Lord Qinghai has done wrong,
清海公虽然有过
his loyalty is...
但论及他待您之心
Your Majesty places great trust
霁风馆乃是陛下的
in Jifeng Pavilion.
心腹要害
If one man from Jifeng Pavilion
此处要是出现了
goes rogue,
重大的疏漏
no feat can offset
就算是有再大的功劳
the damage it causes.
也是难以抵消的
Please punish Lord Qinghai
恳请陛下惩处清海公
and screen the staff of Jifeng Pavilion.
彻查霁风馆
- Please punish Lord Qinghai
请陛下惩处清海公
Your Majesty,
陛下
I request to be dismissed.
臣自请革职
Denied!
不准
It’s not the first time you’ve asked for a dismissal.
动不动就自请革职
What do you take me and the court for?
你把朕和朝堂当什么了
It’s true
清海公
that Lord Qinghai was wronged last time.
上次的确是被判误
But this is different.
但此次不同
Your Majesty mustn’t keep a potential traitor by your side.
陛下 切莫养虎为患哪
Enough!
够啦
During the fake princess’s treason,
伪帝姬谋逆时
were it not for Lord Qinghai,
若不是清海公
would I even have been able to sit here?
朕今日还能坐在这儿吗
Each and every one of you
你们一个个
is loud now,
现在喊得大声
but if you were there,
那个时候
you would have fled, wouldn’t you?
就差钻进地洞了吧
Your Majesty,
陛下
I’m grateful for your grace.
蒙您不弃
But being in a critical position,
但臣身处要职
I deserve a fair punishment more than anyone else.
更需要您公平处置
So I ask
臣自请
to stand guard at the North Palace Gate
调到北宫门外职守
and reflect on my issues.
静思己过
I said you won’t be punished, and you won’t.
朕说不罚就不罚
What you do is up to you.
你想怎么做是你的事
The assembly is over.
退朝
- Good day, Your Majesty.
恭送陛下
Good day, Your Majesty.
给陛下请安
What did you cook?
做了什么
It smells so good.
怪香的
Marinated quail,
糟鹌鹑
with sesame oil and seeds.
用香油和芝麻拌的
What’s this?
这是什么
Congee with long wheat,
粳米里放了长麦
lotus seeds and shredded chicken.
莲子和鸡丝
It calms the mind and warms the stomach.
可以宁神暖胃
I had
朕今日
a terrible day.
很不开心
I know.
缇兰知道
Anyone in court
朝廷里那帮人
whom I can give
但凡有朕
my absolute trust to
可亲可相信的人
is subject to constant impeachments.
总有人来构陷
They’re trying to turn me against him.
想让他与朕离心
They will not stop
不让朕成为
until they make me
真正的孤家寡人
a real loner.
他们是不会罢手的
There won’t be a day
陛下是不会有
when Your Majesty becomes
成为真正的孤家寡人的
a loner.
那一日的
With your permission,
只要陛下愿意
I will always be here for you.
缇兰会一直陪着您
Will you?
是吗
Until when?
到何时
Until the end of time.
到时间尽头
Then it’s a deal.
那便说定了
Lord,
公爷
His Majesty has decreed that you will not be punished.
陛下已经下旨不罚您
Why are you doing this?
您这是何苦呢
When standing guard,
值岗之时
we’re not allowed to chat or move freely.
不准私自言语行动
Lord Chang.
昶王殿下
Lord Qinghai,
清海公
I’m so sorry that I couldn’t
季昶有愧于清海公
stop those officials
没能劝阻那些大臣
from fanning anger.
煽风点火
Your Highness is so kind.
殿下不必放在心上
Please, Your Highness.
殿下请
You must serve Lord Qinghai
你们侍奉清海公
wholeheartedly.
务必用心
If anything goes wrong,
万一出什么差错
I will
本王
not spare you.
头一个饶不了你们
Yes.
是
Eunuch Mu,
穆内官
Consort Shurong has returned to Yu’an Palace.
淑容妃已经回愈安宫了
Your Majesty,
陛下
Please go back to the palace and rest.
陛下也回宫歇息吧
Is Lord Qinghai
清海公
still standing guard at the North Palace Gate?
还在北宫门外职守吗
Your Majesty,
回陛下的话
Lord Qinghai is still there.
清海公还在
I guess he will be there
怕是近些时候
for some time.
都会如此了
What a headstrong man!
真是天生的倔种
He has to make a fool of himself.
非要自取其辱
Your Majesty,
陛下
perhaps Lord Qinghai is doing this
许是清海公这样做
to ease public anger,
也是为了平息众怒
so that they won’t put too much pressure
好让陛下在群臣面前
on Your Majesty.
有个交代吧
By the way...
对了
Tomorrow,
明日
tell the Directorate of Astronomy
宣朕的旨意
to choose an auspicious day,
让钦天监选个吉日
and Fabric Office and Imperial Manufactories
再令绫锦司跟少府监
to provide the Empress’s daily use
按照继后仪制
to Consort Shurong.
备办淑容妃的一应用度
Yes, Your Majesty.
奴婢谨遵旨意
Eunuch Mu.
穆内官
Isn’t it against the rules
按继后的仪制
to provide the Empress’s daily use
置办淑容妃的备办用度
to a consort?
岂不是僭越了
Silly lad,
傻皮子
don’t you get it?
这还不明白啊
The Empress’s Palace has been vacant for years.
中宫之位空悬多年
Soon, it won’t be.
这样的日子快到头了
You’ll see.
你瞅着吧
The mistress
愈安宫里啊
of Yu’an Palace
肯定会出一位
will soon become the Empress.
正经的主子
Good evening, Your Highness.
参见昶王殿下
Has anyone seen you coming?
可曾被人察觉
Don’t worry, Your Highness.
殿下放心
I made sure I wasn’t tailed
必定是干干净净
before I came in.
才进的王府
Mr. Fu,
符大人办事
you’re so reassuring.
就是让人放心啊
This prey of ours
这次的猎物
is quite resilient.
能屈能伸
His self-punishment
此番苦肉计
gives me no chance to do anything.
让本王简直难以下手啊
Your Highness shouldn’t worry.
殿下又何需忧心呢
Any man
只要是人
has his weaknesses.
便有弱点
When we find his,
掐住弱点
he will no longer fight back.
便再无还击之力了
You’re very perceptive,
你倒是通透
unlike your former master,
不像你家主子那般
who only knew to confront Fang Jianming.
只会跟方鉴明蛮干
Thank you for the compliment.
殿下谬赞
As long as Your Highness
只要殿下
agrees to avenge General Su’s death,
愿为苏将军报仇
I, Fu Yi,
符义
am at Your Highness’s disposal.
任凭殿下差遣
Last time you reported
上回你说
you had something on Fang Jianming.
有方鉴明的把柄
Tell me about it.
说说看
Lord Qinghai’s
清海公
favorite apprentice, Fang Haishi,
最中意的徒儿方海市
coughed blood and had a fever.
吐血高热
I invited a physician to check his pulse
臣曾在赤山城
in Chishan City.
为她延医把脉
The physician said
郎中说
that Fang Haishi is a woman.
方海市是女儿家
It’s inevitable that her health will take a blow.
气血两虚 在所难免
You mean...
你是说
Fang Haishi is a woman.
方海市是女子
Have you confirmed it?
可曾确证
She once spent some time
她曾在黄泉营
at Huangquan Battalion.
待过些时日
But she never shared a tent,
从不与人同眠
or a bath with others.
从不与人同浴
I thought she was
符某先前以为
just a spoiled young master.
是公子习气
When I think about it again,
现在想想
who would behave like this
若非女子
except for a woman?
又怎会如此
I also found out
臣还曾打探
that Fang Haishi never
方海市生病
sought a physician’s treatment.
从不延医诊治
Even when she was wounded,
即便受伤
she treated herself.
也是独自处理
The physicians in Huangquan Battalion
连黄泉营的医官
have never treated her.
都未曾察看过
Well,
那
where is the physician from Chishan City?
那郎中人呢
We got the confirmation,
既然事实确凿
so there’s no reason to keep him alive.
闲杂人等 留之何用
Good.
好
Your Highness,
殿下
His Majesty refuses to listen to advice.
如今陛下任性
The officials’ effort is vain.
群臣劝谏虽然无用
But Prince Duohan of Huku
可鹄库王子夺罕
attacked His Majesty
潜伏多年
after years of lurking,
行刺陛下后
and had just fled to Huku.
刚刚逃回鹄库
The aftermath isn’t over.
事态尚未平息
Now we found Fang Haishi faked her identity
方海市假扮男子
during the Imperial Examination,
参加科举
and was later conferred as General of Cloud-like Flag,
后又被封为云麾将军
a high-rank officer.
官职实属不低
Fang Jianming covered her up
方鉴明故意隐藏其身份
and deceived His Majesty.
这是无可推脱的
There’s no excuse for this.
欺君大罪
With two crimes on his head,
这罪上加罪
I’m sure he won’t get away.
想必他是逃也逃不过了
Fang Jianming
方鉴明
wins the absolute trust of His Majesty.
平日深得陛下信任
Judging by his counter strikes,
此番他见招拆招
I guess he has seen it coming.
应该是早就有所察觉
No rush.
不急在一时
Never let your rival know
永远不要让对手知道
what moves you’re going to make.
你要出什么招式
We have time.
慢慢来